Hi, welcome back to
Nagarjuna, course #3.
What we're really exploring
is the Medicine Buddha,
the emptiness of Medicine Buddha,
and the emptiness of the
Medicine Buddha mantras.
Why?
Not something weird and
it's not philosophy.
It's not philosophy.
I'm not asking you to learn
some ancient philosophy.
I just want you to know
how to get your mantras to work.
Because isn't that the whole goal?
And if we don't understand
how things work,
then we don't understand how mantras work.
And then you can say mantras
and they don't work as well.
So here we go.
This chapter has a funny name,
and it's SNGA ROL NA GNAS PA BRTAG PA.
We're on chapter nine. Now
we're starting a new chapter.
We did an eight-chapter review already,
and this second class is
all about the ninth chapter.
SNGA ROL NA means before, before.
GNAS PA means what was sitting
there before.
"What was there before" is
the name of this chapter.
It's a cute name of a chapter.
What was there before?
What do you mean what was there before?
I'm going to tell you,
don't worry about it.
SNGA ROL NA GNAS PA BRTAG PA
Let's go to the first verse.
It says
,LTA DANG NYAN LA SOGS PA DANG,
,TSOR SOGS DANG YANG DBANG BYAS PA,
,GANG GI YIN PA DE DAG GI
,SNGA ROL DE YOD KHA CIG SMRA,
Now, you have to know
something about Nagarjuna.
His style, in this book called Wisdom,
is that sometimes he writes a
little poem about a bad idea,
and then he attacks it.
But he doesn't tell you
which poem is the bad idea
and which poem is the good idea.
So that's one of the frustrating
things about this book.
He'll do a little poem
about a stupid idea,
and since we're just babies, we think,
"Oh, that sounds good to me",
and then later he attacks it.
So you've got to... It's
a very difficult thing
that the first verse in this chapter
called "What was there before" is wrong.
It's another guy's position.
And then Nagarjuna's going to attack it.
So get used to it, KHA CIG.
The other guy is GZHAN LUGS.
The other guy's position
sometimes comes first.
Now here's the other guy's position.
And as we go through these chapters,
I'm going to take you through the verses.
They're not very long, and it's a blessing
to hear the verses.
To explain them in detail would
take approximately 20 years.
Seriously. But we're
going to get the main idea
of each verse and then
we're going to go on.
So, here we go, let's get
the verse up you guys.
LTA DANG NYAN LA SOGS PA means:
LTA means when you look at something,
NYAN means when you hear something,
et cetera, et cetera SOGS PA
meaning, when you smell something,
taste something, feel something.
And then TSOR BA,
your capacity of feeling,
I feel good. I feel bad.
It hurts. It feels nice.
And YANG DBANG BYAS PA,
DBANG BYAS PA means all the various parts
of your mind and mental functions,
which have the power to do something,
which have power, DBANG BYAS PA,
which assert power on other things.
GANG GI YIN PA is extremely difficult.
It means the corresponding.
The corresponding.
What do you mean the corresponding?
Well, when you're talking
about your eye, E-Y-E,
and you're looking at the carrot juice,
then... okay, here we go...
the corresponding object.
So the eye and the corresponding object
is called GANG GI YIN PA.
GANG GI YIN PA
Here it's called GANG GI YIN PA.
DE DAG GI SNGA ROL YOD
And this is a position by another guy
who says there must be an eye there
before the corresponding object.
There must be an eye, E-Y-E, there
If you're saying mantras
to the Medicine Buddha,
if you're saying the name
of the Medicine Buddha,
then you have to be there
before you can say the mantras, right?
That's what the other guy says.
A mantra sayer has to be
there before the mantra.
The person who says the
mantra has to be there
before the mantra is said.
The mantra sayer has to
sit down on his meditation
or her meditation cushion,
and then she can say a mantra.
So which came first,
the chicken or the egg?
Which came first, the
mantra or the mantra sayer?
This school says,
obviously, the mantra sayer
has to be on his cushion or her cushion
before they say the mantra.
Now, whose position is that?
KHA CIG SMRA
KHA CIG SMRA means some guys say,
some guys say. And by the way,
we're going to have
different positions here.
And then Choney Lama
and the great commentators
have identified the guy
who said this first
verse, and it's called,
it's a group called Samitya.
Samitya
This is an ancient group
of monks who followed
or they split off from a school
called Sarvastivada.
These are the very, very,
very early monks of Buddhism.
They broke into different schools.
They had the patch of their school
sewn to the top of their robes,
and then this is the samitya
which means highly respected
because they followed a teacher
called Highly Respected,
Mr. Highly Respected.
So these Abhidharma guys, basically,
they have the opinion that
the person saying the mantra
should be there before the mantra.
Somebody... Don't forget,
the name of this chapter
is "Who was there first",
who was there before.
And if we put it in terms
of seeing something,
there has to be somebody there to look
before you can see something.
The person has to come in
the room, open their eyes,
and then they see something.
The person has to come first.
Then what they see comes after that,
in the order of things.
And the mantra should... Sorry,
the person should sit down on
their cushion to do a mantra
before the mantra comes out.
That person has to sit down. Like that.
That's the first school's position.
As I said, this position is mistaken.
And Nagarjuna, strangely,
starts out the chapter
with the wrong idea.
And just get used to it.
And of course at least a lot of arguments.
I'm going to put a picture
here of an astronomer.
So according to this school,
when a guy goes out to use a
telescope to look at the stars,
it must be that before
the stars were observed,
we had a young girl.
So in the top picture,
the girl went outside
with her telescope at night
and she put it up to her eye.
And she must have come first.
The E-Y-E, the eye. And
then, there was a seeing.
There was an astronoming.
There was a watching of the stars.
First, there is the
girl with the telescope,
and then the next moment,
you can have a girl watching the stars.
That's the position of
the Abhidharma guys.
They're some kind of Abhidharma guy.
If you're interested
about all those obscure
Abhidharma schools,
don't forget to read Ben
Kramer's Mixed Nuts text.
And in Tibetan this school
is called MANG BKUR BA
SAMMITYA
Let's go on to the next...
Oh, by the way, sorry.
Let's do the second verse here.
The second verse starts
with DNGOS PO.
Second verse, chapter nine.
DNGOS PO YOD PA MA YIN NA
Now the verse says, if
there's no seeing there,
DNGOS PO YOD PA MA YIN NA
and you have to know that
seeing here means the eye.
It's confusing.
If the actor, if the thing doing something
is not there,
if the girl doesn't step
outside with her telescope,
then who's going to be looking?
How can you have a looking at the stars
before she walks out with her telescope?
Therefore, before there's a looking,
there must be a looker.
That's their position.
DE PHYIR DE DAG SNGA ROL NA
DNGOS PO GNAS PA DE YOD DO
Therefore, the girl with
the telescope must exist
before the observing with
the telescope can take place.
And that feels comfortable to us.
That feels pretty correct to us.
All right, let's go on
to verse number three.
Where are you?
And by the way, we're
going to have two arguments
to argue against Buddhists,
but lower Buddhists.
And here's our first argument.
Okay, here we go.
,LTA DANG NYAN LA SOGS PA DANG,
,TSOR BA LA SOGS NYID KYI NI,
,SNGA ROL DNGOS PO GANG GNAS PA,
,DE NI GANG GIS GDAGS PAR BYA,
LTA DANG NYAN LA SOGS PA
DANG means... and by the way,
many of the ninth chapter
verses start with looking,
hearing, smelling, tasting,
healing, et cetera,
TSOR BA LA SOGS NYID KYI NI
and sensation: feeling something,
feeling good, feeling happy, feeling sad.
SNGA ROL DNGOS PO GANG GNAS PA
- Okay, according to
you, the girl walked out
with her telescope first, right?
- Yeah, yeah, she was
first, and then there was...
then there was a telescoping,
then somebody was watching the stars.
- Okay, well, when she walked out,
how did you know she was
a girl with a telescope?
- Huh?
- How did you know she was
a girl with a telescope?
- Well, she had a telescope in her hand.
- But wait, why is it a telescope?
What's a telescope?
- A telescope's something
something you use
to watch the stars.
- Oh, so you don't know it's a telescope
until you use it, right?
- Yeah. Maybe it doesn't
look like a telescope,
but once you use it to watch
the stars, it's a telescope.
- Okay, so she walked out
with a stick in her hand then.
It wasn't a telescope, was it?
- No, it was a telescope.
- How do you know it's a telescope?
- It looked like a telescope.
- Look, lots of things
look like telescopes.
I own a telescope.
You don't know if it's a
telescope until somebody uses it
to look at a star, got it?
- Right. So which came first,
the girl with the telescope
or the looking at the star?
- Looking at the star.
How can you call it a
telescope if she doesn't use it
to look at a star?
I don't know, it could be a chocolate bar
and it looks like a telescope.
We don't know.
Until she uses it to look at
a star, it's not a telescope.
Therefore if you asked "Which came first,
the astronomer or the star?"
The star. Why?
GDAGS PAR BYA
Last line.
GDAGS PAR BYA means you can't call her
an astronomer until she looks at an astra,
until she looks at a star.
So, therefore, looking
at the star came first,
and then the girl came.
Why?
You can't call her an astronomer
until she looks at the star.
Therefore, it's not that a
girl who is an astronomer
walked out and looked at the star.
Somebody walked out with a
stick, she looked at stars,
and now we know the stick is a
telescope in the next moment.
So which came first, the
telescope or the star?
The star.
What you saw came first.
Don't tell me the girl
has to be there first,
it's not even possible.
Who are we complaining to?
These Abhidharma guys.
It's a kind of Abhidharma guy.
That's our first refutation of his idea.
So look, Tim, we can finish a class in
less than two hours. I'm going to...
By the way, the picture I like here...
here's a picture.
You're going to like this picture
of me and... sorry...Veronica
and this guy.
What's going on in this picture?
Me and Veronica are
making the down payment
for the Black Hole Cafe,
for the cafe that we bought.
This was two years ago.
Why is that guy smiling such a big smile?
Because he got rid of the cafe!
And they're receiving their first payment.
Jigme was the banker.
She did all the financial stuff.
And what do you have here?
Who is this guy?
He's the guy taking the check.
By the way, this guy...
I used to go down there
almost every day to this
tiny cafe near my house.
Keep the photo up! And there's this quiet,
very likable guy pouring coffee.
And I even thought he
might be a little retarded
or something, because he
would never say anything,
and he'd just smile and
pour the coffee, you know?
And I'd say, well, that's so nice,
they hired someone who
can't do anything else,
and he's pouring coffee. And then
I mentioned it to somebody.
He said, "Listen,
"Ralph is one of the most
famous astronomers in the world.
"He just got back from...
"he just got back from
installing an advanced telescope
"on a 747 that's going to
fly around the world all day.
"He's got it rigged so that
it moves as the plane moves,
"so the star stays in it.
"And they're going to observe asteroids
"that might bang into the
Earth, and without him,
"they might bang into the Earth."
And then I'm like, "Wow,
I thought he was just serving coffee."
Why didn't I know he was an astronomer?
Because he wasn't looking at stars.
Therefore, stars come first, right?
It's not that Ralph came first.
Ralph came second.
I mean, Ralph, the
astronomer, came second.
By the way, that lady is teaching me.
That's his wife, Kay, who we call Cricket.
I can't tell you the story
that when they went to their honeymoon,
the guy who owned the hotel
said, "Don't lose that Cricket.
"She going to drop out
of the sheets and..."
Because she's very short.
Anyway, that's why they called the cafe
Cricket's Cafe.
So anyway... That's
not a bad thing to say.
She let me say that.
So our objection
is that, look, you don't
know Ralph's an astronomer
until he looks at a star
and then you know who he is.
Next verse.
This is our second argument
against that lower Abhidharma position.
,LTA BA LA SOGS MED PAR YANG,
,GAL TE DE NI GNAS GYUR NA,
,DE MED PAR YANG DE DAG NI,
,YOD PAR 'GYUR BAR THE TSOM MED,
This is tricky.
I've got to get it straight.
LTA BA LA SOGS MED PAR YANG
If Ralph was an astronomer
before he pulled out his telescope,
if the girl who came
outside with the telescope
was already an astronomer
before she looked at the stars -
got it? -
then looking at the stars
could be there without her.
Okay? (chuckles)
I'll say it again and it's confusing.
If the girl came out first
and she was an astronomer
without looking at the
stars, and then later
she looked at the stars,
and if she came first
and looking at the stars came second,
then looking at the stars
doesn't really depend on her.
And if she didn't come out,
there would be somebody
looking at the stars.
Got it?
That's our second argument
against this second.
And now there's the next verse,
which is verse number five.
,CI YIS GANG ZHIG GSAL BAR BYED,
,GANG GIS CI ZHIG GSAL BAR BYED,
,CI MED GANG ZHIG GA LA YOD,
,GANG MED CI ZHIG GA LA YOD,
This is tricky.
The CI YIS means what actions,
such as looking at the stars, GSAL BAR,
who? What action defines what person?
So who is it being defined
by looking at the star?
Well, the astronomer.
Who gets defined by looking at the stars?
The astronomer.
And there's a very important
word here, and we're going to,
I don't know, can we
detour to the Sanskrit?
This is a great place
to go to the Sanskrit.
I'm not going to bother
you much in this class,
but I really encourage you to, come on,
learn some Sanskrit while
you're in this easiest book
to read in Sanskrit of all.
While you're inside this book,
why not pick up a few Sanskrit words.
So here's the word, here we go, ajyate.
You won't find it in a dictionary.
So √aj is a root, and you
see the square root sign,
means that's a verbal root.
Sanskrit has 800 verbal roots,
so if you memorize them,
you know Sanskrit.
I did that on the bus going
to New York. So anyway,
√aj, √aj means to drive
something or push something.
So √aj means to push something.
I think engine comes from this.
Not everybody agrees,
but... Can you keep it up?
Because I'm not there.
So ajyate means push, meaning,
which action sketches in,
which action propels an astronomer?
Which looking at the stars,
Was it the looking at the stars
which ajyated the astronomer
or was it the astronomer
who ajyated the stars,
looking at the stars?
Did the astronomer look at the stars
or did looking at the stars
create this astronomer,
make them an astronomer?
Which one?
Both.
But they come in a different order!
What you're seeing,
the result is the cause
or the cause is the result?
What? What are you trying to say?
The point is it's confusing.
Yeah, something's fishy.
Saying Medicine Buddha
mantras doesn't heal people.
It's not a mantra until
somebody gets healed.
You don't say the mantra first
and then it heals somebody.
It's not a mantra until
it has a magical effect.
That's the definition of mantra.
So which came first, the
mantra or the healing?
I don't know, well the mantra came first.
I said the mantra and then
the person got healed.
Well then you don't
understand what's going on
because until a person gets
healed, it's not a mantra.
- How can the person get
healed before I say the mantra?
- Well, that's not possible
either, so what's really
going on? The mantra
doesn't touch the healing.
And the healing is not
touched by the mantra.
The mantra doesn't cause the healing
and the healing is not
caused by the mantra.
The mantra and the healing
are in completely separate timeframes.
They never touch each other.
The mantra is gone by the
time the healing starts.
The healing starts...the
healing can't start
until the mantra ends.
The healing can't start
until the mantra is gone
and the mantra can't do anything
until it heals somebody.
It's weird. Something's fishy.
Everything you think
about how the Medicine Buddha
mantra works is mistaken.
So how much power could
it have to sit there
and say a mantra?
CI YIS GANG ZHIG GSAL BAR BYED
Is it the saying of the mantra
that makes you a mantra sayer
or is it a mantra sayer
who makes a mantra?
CI MED GANG ZHIG GA LA YOD
If you didn't have a healing,
how could you have a mantra reciter?
And if you didn't have a mantra reciter,
how could you have a healing? Got it?
But they never touch each other.
Therefore, you could say a mantra today,
and 10 million years from
now something will happen,
because they don't have to touch!
They never touch.
Don't get confused and
don't get worried. The point is, what?
We confuse you first
and then we clear it up.
And then you never forget.
So if you're feeling confused right now,
you're in the right place.
Now, was it that someone confused you
or you were confused
before they confused you?
That we have to talk about.
So what have we got here
in the next picture?
Pachi, I don't remember...
Are you going to have an
astronomer without a telescope?
Who put the name astronomer on them
if they don't have a telescope yet?
If they're not using a telescope yet,
how can you call them an astronomer?
You just put a sign there
that says "astronomer"?
They've got nothing in
their hands, got it?
But they're an astronomer.
Why? Because I call them astronomer.
So look, they don't have
to look at the stars
to be an astronomer, right?
Right. If Geshe Michael
says they're astronomer,
they're astronomer.
Their hands are empty. They
are not looking at the stars.
Yeah, okay, good.
So is it the looking at the stars
that makes you an astronomer?
Or do you call someone an astronomer
and then they look at the stars?
Which comes first, the chicken or the egg?
You've got to think about it.
And if you understand it,
then your mantras will work better.
Next verse, you guys, verse #6.
And by the way, without warning you,
by the way, anticipatory translation.
If I tell you Nagarjuna hasn't warned you,
what can you guess about the next verse?
It's wrong.
Then he goes, he has a wrong
verse, two correct ones,
and then he pops you
with another wrong one,
but he doesn't tell you.
That's why you need Choney Lama.
And if you don't have Choney Lama,
God bless you.
I once listened to a
person explain this text
for like six months.
Yeah, anyway.
,LTA LA SOGS PA THAMS CAD KYI,
,SNGA ROL GANG ZHIG YOD PA MIN,
,LTA SOGS NANG NAS GZHAN ZHIG GIS,
,GZHAN GYI TSE NA GSAL BAR BYED,
,LTA LA SOGS PA THAMS CAD KYI,
,SNGA ROL GANG ZHIG YOD PA MIN,
Then the guy comes up with
a weird thing, you ready?
We've been talking about seeing, hearing,
smelling, tasting,
feeling. And he says, look,
if you have stars, then you
can say there's an astronomer.
But you can't say there's a listener.
If you have someone looking at stars,
you can say there's an astronomer.
If you limit it to one sense:
seeing, hearing, smelling,
the guy says, "Look, I'm not
saying the person is there
with all their senses first
because they're seeing.
Let's divide the senses up.
A sense organ is not an organ
until it does its thing,
but that doesn't prove
anything about the other ones."
If you see something,
you can call it an eye,
but that doesn't say
anything about the ear.
Got it?
Let's treat them separately.
Let's keep it separately.
If you have a seeing,
then you have an eye.
But I'm not saying if you have a seeing,
you have an ear.
That's another thing.
Let's divide the senses out,
and each one is operating.
When the eye is operating
towards the stars,
it's not that you're
listening to somebody else
in the room.
That's separate.
Then if somebody in the room
clears their throat loudly,
then you stop looking at the star
and you start listening to the person.
And then at that time, the eye shuts down
and we cannot say there is a seer
because there's nothing
seen because you switched
to another object.
So it's never that you have
five senses at the same time.
One of them is working at a certain time,
and then you can say there's a hearer
or there's a seer.
,LTA LA SOGS PA THAMS CAD KYI,
,SNGA ROL GANG ZHIG YOD PA MIN,
It's not that you have
all your senses operating,
and then before then, you have
five senses ready to operate.
That's not the case.
,LTA SOGS NANG NAS GZHAN ZHIG GIS,
,GZHAN GYI TSE NA GSAL BAR BYED,
Among, NANG NAS,
among seeing, et cetera,
when one of them is in operation,
then it GSAL BAR BYED.
It defines or it delineates a sense power.
When there's a seeing...
sorry, when you see something,
there's a seer.
When you hear something, there's a hearer.
But it's not that there's a hearer or seer
waiting there to do something, before.
He's trying to clarify.
Here we go.
The picture is,
we are spotlighting or we
are, what do you call that?
Spotlighting one sense... spotlighting?
Yeah, we're focusing
in on one sense organ,
and then you can say,
when it's in operation,
it's a sense organ, but the
others are not in operation.
Hearing, for example, and
when it's not working yet,
so you can't say about
it that there's a hearer
and something heard.
Now we go to verse 7-9.
Am I right?
This is our refutation of that idea
that if we treat the senses separately,
we can talk about a seer
before something is seen
or something seen.
We can say there was a seer first,
and then there was a seeing second.
,LTA LA SOGS PA THAMS CAD KYI,
,SNGA ROL GAL TE YOD MIN NA,
If the seer and all are not there,
if you don't have all the senses there
before there's any
seeing, hearing, smelling,
tasting, touching,
,LTA LA SOGS PA RE RE YI,
,SNGA ROL DE NI JI LTAR YOD,
if all five senses are not there
before all five experiences,
then how can you say
that one is there before its experience?
It doesn't makes sense.
It doesn't make sense to isolate the eyes
and say that it's seeing.
It's an eye before it sees,
but the others are not hearing,
smelling, tasting, feeling
before they do those things.
It doesn't make sense
to treat one differently
from the other ones.
,LTA PO DE NYID NYAN PO DE,
If that's the way it worked,
then when the eye is a looker,
it's also a hearer and a smeller
and a taster and a feeler.
,LTA PO DE NYID NYAN PO DE,
,GAL TE TSOR PO'ANG DE NYID NA,
,RE RE'I SNGA ROL YOD GYUR NA,
,DE NI DE LTAR MI RIGS SO,
So then in that case,
then feeling too could be
feeling before you feel,
or feeling wouldn't be feeling
until you felt something.
You wouldn't have feelings
until they got hurt, according to you,
because you're looking at something.
And you can only have one thing
doing something right now.
,GAL TE LTA PO GZHAN NYID LA,
,NYAN PA PO GZHAN TSOR GZHAN NA,
,LTA PO YOD TSE NYAN POR 'GYUR,
,BDAG KYANG MANG PO NYID DU 'GYUR,
If your ears had the capacity to hear,
even as your eye was looking at something,
then, and if they were
operating separately,
then as you were looking at something,
you would be hearing something.
If you have five separate senses
and each one is not a sense
until it senses something,
and only the one which is
sensing something right now
is a sense,
and those other four senses
are just sitting there
doing nothing, and they're not themselves
until they sense something, then
since you call them senses already,
they must be self-existently senses
before they sense something.
You're the one who said
you had to sense something
before we could call you a sense.
And you said if one of the
five senses was sensing,
then that was a sense and the
other senses weren't senses
until they were sensing
something. But they are senses
because they could sense something,
so the other four are there.
They're not senses in
operation, but they are senses.
Well, and only one can
work at a time. Right.
Okay, so there's five Tims.
There's five Tims sitting in that chair
right there, right now. There's five Tims.
Why?
It's a sense before it senses something
because you said it's
a sense sitting there
waiting to be an active sense. Got it?
So each sense according
to you can only work
at its own time period.
So Tim's senses, Tim's
eye sense is active,
and that's active Tim, and
there's four other Tims
sitting in the chair waiting to be Tim.
Or they're Tim but they're not Tim yet.
Then because they're not
doing what Tim does yet.
Okay, that's okay, this
is five Tims in the chair
and one of them is doing something, right?
Right.
Then there's five Tims.
There's too many.
Then Tim should buy eight more shoes.
So, here you go. And by the way,
these are not silly,
stupid, little things.
They're very deep.
If you think they're
silly, you didn't get it.
We have a room full of mes here,
Pachi, somewhere?
I mean it's just a nice picture.
It took me a while to find it.
I'm sorry she's so dressed up.
I can only find one picture like this.
But there should be a
separate lady for each sense
that she has.
One for hearing, one for
seeing, one for tasting.
All right, next verse, where are we?
Sorry?
We're on ten, and there's no image here
because it's kind of a just...
,LTA DANG NYAN LA SOGS PA DANG,
,TSOR BA DAG LA SOGS PA DANG,
,GANG LAS 'GYUR BA'I 'BYUNG DE LA'ANG,
,DE NI YOD PA MA YIN NO,
Your physical senses, for example,
come from chemicals.
Not your mind, but the eyeball,
and the auditory canal,
and the cells on the
inside of the nostril,
and the cells on the tongue,
and the cells of the skin
that feels things.
Those come from chemicals.
Now Buddhism says that
mind has to come from mind,
and mind cannot come from
something which is not mind.
But the sense powers,
which do the sensing,
those are physical.
They come from chemicals.
Now, if the object that
wasn't active isn't a sense,
if your eye is not a sense power
until it sees something,
If your eye is not... if the
astronomer's not an astronomer
until they look at a star,
if the person doing the
mantra is not a mantra expert
until they say a mantra,
then the causes of those things,
the chemicals that create
your auditory nerve,
the carbon, the oxygen, the nitrogen,
they can't be there either
because there's no sense power.
So the physical basis of
your senses, the chemicals,
according to you, if the sense power,
which is not in the operation
is not a sense power yet,
then it doesn't come from its chemicals.
It comes from sensing.
It does not come from chemicals.
If when the ear is
inactive it's not an ear,
then the things which created
the ear must also be gone,
and there cannot be any
chemicals which created the ear
because there's no ear. Why?
It's not hearing anything.
Okay, got it. Why?
Because only the eye can see something.
When the eye sees something,
the ear has to wait to hear something,
and during that period,
the ear doesn't exist.
And therefore, you must be
saying the chemicals don't exist
and you're not sitting
on your ass right now.
And that's Nagarjuna, not me.
I mean, he didn't say
people, but you get it.
,LTA DANG NYAN LA SOGS PA DANG,
,TSOR BA DAG LA SOGS PA DANG,
,GANG LAS 'GYUR BA'I 'BYUNG DE LA'ANG,
The causes from which they come,
meaning the four elements,
which we call chemicals.
,DE NI YOD PA MA YIN NO,
So those are not possible either.
There must be no carbon in your body. Why?
Because your ear doesn't have
carbon at that moment. Why?
Because it's not there when
it's not in operation. Why?
Because only the eye can be in operation.
When the eye is in
operation, we call it an eye
because of what it sees, but
we can't talk about the ear yet
because it's not doing anything.
Therefore the ear is not there right then.
Okay, so there's no carbon,
there's no oxygen, right?
Got it?
Think about it.
How do you relate that to mantras?
Only the mantra being
said right now is a mantra
and all the other mantras I ever learned
are not mantras right now? Why?
Because they're not
doing anything right now.
So of all the mantras you know,
only one can be a mantra at a time,
and the others are nothing.
When you're saying it, it's a mantra.
When it's helping somebody, it's a mantra.
And when you're not using the mantra,
it's not a mantra.
And it has no sound. Got it?
Verse 11. Yay.
,LTA DANG NYAN LA SOGS PA DANG,
,TSOR BA DAG LA SOGS PA YANG,
,GANG GI YIN PA GAL TE MED,
,DE DAG KYANG NI YOD MA YIN,
What the heck is this one?
Let's see the commentary.
BLANG BYA LTA BA SOGS DE
DAG KYANG NI CHOS CAN,
NGO BO NYID KYIS YOD PA MA YIN TE,
Okay, good.
If the sense power is not a sense power
until it's doing something,
then we already discussed
why the physical chemicals
of that sense power, like the chemicals
that make the eyeball,
would have to be absent
at that time also. But
the result of those things
would also have to be not
possible, meaning, hearing itself.
If the ear is only the ear
when you're hearing something,
which is what he said, then
when you're seeing something,
the ear can't be there.
A hearing can't be there. - Right!
If hearing can't be there and
then no ear could be there.
Right. And no chemicals that
make the ear could be there
because there's no ear there. Right.
Then, by the way, there's
no hearing either.
The cause of the ear couldn't be there
and the result of the ear, hearing,
couldn't be there either.
The ear can't be there,
the chemicals in the ear
can't be there, and the
function of the ear, hearing,
can't be there. Why?
Because you're looking at something.
According to you, you're
looking at something.
Something can be defined by
functioning at the moment,
but it doesn't apply
to all the other senses
at the same time,
can not, according to this guy.
I think we've got one more verse here.
Did we lose everybody? Yeah!
By the way, the 12th verse,
which I think is the
final verse, right Tim?
It's a summary. It's a summary
of the chapter. Thank God.
At least if we understand the summary,
we can say we know the chapter.
So, let's look at the summary.
,GANG ZHIG LTA LA SOGS PA YI,
,SNGA ROL DA LTA PHYI NA MED,
,DE LA YOD DO MED DO ZHES,
,RTOG PA DAG NI LDOG PAR 'GYUR,
And I like this image
because I like ice cream,
but I never get it because
my wife doesn't let me
Oh, I'm not... We've got three choices.
Don't quote me.
You've got three kinds of ice cream?
Yeah, okay.
Look, this is a summary of the chapter.
If you understand the next
two minutes, you're okay.
And I think you will. So no pressure.
There's three kinds of ice cream here.
You've got to choose
between the peppermint,
the lemon, and the chocolate.
Makes me want to choose one.
So there's three different ideas
in this whole chapter,
and Nagarjuna kindly is
wrapping it up for us.
He said, look, there's three ideas.
If you get these three, don't worry about
what you didn't understand, all right?
What are these three?
Can a seer exist before
they see? Yes or no?
Can you call someone an astronomer
until they look at the stars?
No, cannot. So that's okay. Why?
%BDAG BYA
There's no appellation cause.
There's nothing to call...
there's no reason to
call them an astronomer
until they look at the stars.
So that's okay, we're
okay with that, right?
You have to look at the stars
before we can call you an astronomer.
You have to say the mantras
before we can call you a
Medicine Buddha practitioner.
Something like that.
Now the tricky one.
When the girl's looking at the stars,
is she an astronomer?
In the moment that she's
looking at the stars,
is she an astronomer?
In the moment that the girl
is looking at the stars
with her telescope, can
we call her an astronomer?
Yeah, we just said that.
After she looks at the stars,
we can call her an astronomer.
So in that moment that
she's looking at the stars,
we can call her an astronomer.
All right, good?
Does she ever meet the stars?
Does she ever have contact with the stars?
An image of a star, does
she ever have contact
with the image of a star?
Is there a place in her life
where a star overlaps with astronomer?
Where being a star overlaps
with being an astronomer.
I mean, she might be a star
astronomer, but... right?
So I'll say it again.
While she's looking at the stars,
can you call her an astronomer?
Yeah, I guess so.
Does the astronomer and
the stars ever overlap?
Is any part of her body a star?
Is any part of the star an astronomer?
Can we say they never overlap?
Then in that case, she
can't look at the star.
They never touch each other.
She might also be swimming
in, what do you call it?
Sayulita.
Looking at the stars is swimming
in Sayulita,
because there's no reason
why she'd be astronomer
because they never touch each other.
She never makes contact with stars
because they can't overlap.
No part of her can become a star
and no part of a star can become her.
Therefore, they have to be
separate and disconnected.
If they're disconnected,
then when she eats a banana,
she's an astronomer.
Because there's no more compelling reason
that looking at the star
should make her an astronomer
if it's not related to
astronomers, if they never overlap.
Okay, third ice cream!
You've got the first two ice creams?
I'll repeat the two ice creams
for you.
Until she looks at the star,
she's not an astronomer.
That's the first ice cream.
Okay. I'm okay with that.
While she's looking at the
star, she can't be an astronomer
because the stars never touch her
and she never touches the stars.
If they never touch and she
can still be an astronomer,
then when she's taking a
bath, she's an astronomer.
Okay, third one.
Is it after looking at the
stars that she's an astronomer?
Does looking at the stars come first
and then the astronomer is established
by looking at the stars?
Yeah! Well then she's also established
by pizzas that fly to Mars
because something that
doesn't exist anymore
is making her an astronomer.
The looking at the stars is done
by the time you call her an astronomer,
therefore, anything else
she ever could have done
would also make her an astronomer,
because there's no connection
between looking at the stars
and becoming an astronomer,
because they can't overlap either.
In all three ice cream
cases, it's impossible.
Something is fishy.
This ice cream smells like fish.
This particular ice
cream smells like fish.
Each of those three choices is defective.
Does the mantra cause the healing?
So the mantra comes first.
Or does saying the
mantra cause the healing
and they're going on at the same time?
Or do you have to heal somebody first
and then you can call a mantra.
Because if it doesn't heal anybody,
it's not really a mantra.
Which three?
And Nagarjuna says none of the above.
I'll say it again, let's
do it one more time.
- Which came first? The
mantra or the healing?
- Oh, mantra.
- Okay, so if mantra
came before the healing,
then the healing didn't
have a cause. - Why?
- Because the mantra's gone
by the time you get healed.
Then you've got a healing without a cause.
- No, no, no, okay, the mantra goes on
at the same time as the healing.
- Okay, then the mantra also
causes rice to grow in Pluto.
- Why?
- Because they don't have any connection.
There's no connection between the two.
They can't connect, they cannot overlap.
Saying the mantra and being
healed from the cancer
are always different things.
Saying a mantra is not
getting healed from cancer.
It causes getting healed by cancer.
Getting healed by cancer
comes after the mantra.
They cannot go on at the same time.
They're separate.
It's not that 10% of healing is mantra
and 10% of mantra is healing.
Mantra comes first, and then it stops,
and you get the healing.
Okay, if it stops and
then you get the healing,
then it can't be connected to the healing.
There cannot be a relationship
between the mantra
and the healing because the mantra stopped
before the healing started.
They never overlap.
Then you could just, I don't
know, eat more croissants
and it would heal cancer.
That's my idea.
And then the last possibility is,
it's not a mantra until
somebody gets healed by it,
then you can really call it a mantra.
Okay. So after the mantra's
finished, it's a mantra, right?
A mantra is not a mantra
until it finishes. Why?
Because a mantra's not
a mantra until it heals.
First comes the healing,
then the mantra is a mantra.
Okay, so you don't have
to say the mantra. Why?
Because by the time the healing comes,
the mantra's gone anyway.
You could have just eaten a pizza
and it would have healed the cancer.
None of the three connections
you think is going on
between the mantra and the
healing the cancer is possible.
There's something fishy.
"Oh Geshe-la, just tell us what's going on
and we won't worry about it."
That's not Nagarjuna's style.
He wants you to figure it out.
Yay. Thank God because all the teachers
who don't understand Nagarjuna
really don't have to say
what they don't understand.
You figure it out.
No, we will figure it out.
So, see you in the next class,
on the emptiness of Medicine Buddha.